{"data": [{"id": 1, "question": "Science", "answer": "Science is a systematic and organised attempt to acquire knowledge about the surroundings through observations experiments and verifications.Science"}, {"id": 2, "question": "Scientific Method", "answer": "Several interrelated steps are involved in scientific method. Some of the most significant steps are as followsul liThe systematic observationsli liReasoningli liMathematical modellingli liTheoretical predictionli ulScientific MethodliThe systematic observationsliliReasoningliliMathematical modellingliliTheoretical predictionliThe systematic observationsReasoningMathematical modellingTheoretical prediction"}, {"id": 3, "question": "Physics", "answer": "Physics is a fundamental science concerned with understanding the natural phenomena that occur in our universe.It has many branches such as Mechanics Electromagnetism Thermodynamics Modem Physics etc. Between 1600 and 1900 three broad areas were developed which is together called Classical Physics. These three areas of study are classical mechanics thermodynamics and electromagnetism. But by 1905 it became apparent that classical ideas failed to explain several phenomena. Then some new theories were developed in what is called Modem Physics such as Special Relativity Quantum Mechanics etc.Physics"}, {"id": 4, "question": "Scope and Excitement of Physics", "answer": "The scope of Physics is very broad and covers a wide range of magnitude of physical quantities such as length mass time energy etc.It deals with the macroscopic world like galaxies and universe as well as microscopic world like nucleus of an atom and fundamental particles like electrons protons neutrons etc.Immense excitement is involved in the study of physics since it explains every naturally occuring phenomena with a set of rules so that clear understanding can be achieved. The challenge to carry out imaginative new experiments to unlock the secrets of nature to verify or refute theories is really exciting.Scope and Excitement of Physics"}, {"id": 5, "question": "Physics in Relation to Other Sciences", "answer": "Physics is a very significant branch of science which plays a crucial role in understanding the developments pertaining to the other branches of science such as Chemistry Biology etc."}, {"id": 6, "question": "i Physics in relation to Mathematics", "answer": "Study of physical variables led to the idea of differentiation integration and differential equation. Meaningful interpretation of Mathematics becomes Physics."}, {"id": 7, "question": "ii Physics in relation to Chemistry", "answer": "The concept of Xray diffraction and radioactivity has helped to distinguish between the various solids and to modify the periodic table.Understanding the bonding and the chemical structure of substances is easy with the help of the concept of interactions between various particles."}, {"id": 8, "question": "iii Physics in relation to Astronomy", "answer": "Optical telescopes of reflecting and refracting type enabled man to explore the space around. Discoveries like radio telescopes have revolutionised the study of Astronomy."}, {"id": 9, "question": "iv Physics in relation to Biology", "answer": "The conceptual study of pressure and its measurement has helped us to know blood pressure and hence the functioning of heart. Invention of Xrays developed the field of diagnosis. Electron and optical microscopic designs have revolutionised the study of medical science."}, {"id": 10, "question": "v Physics in relation to Meteorology", "answer": "The discoveries regarding the study of pressure variations help us to forecast the weather.Various other inventions of physics have opened new vistas of study in the field of sciences and social sciences.Physics in Relation to Other Sciencesi Physics in relation to Mathematics.ii Physics in relation to Chemistry.iii Physics in relation to Astronomy.iv Physics in relation to Biology.v Physics in relation to Meteorology."}, {"id": 11, "question": "Physics in Relation to Technology and Society", "answer": "Advancement in physics has led to new technologies and viceversa. Sometimes technology gives rise to new dimension of physics at other times physics generates new technology. In fact the technological development is closely related to the application of science and physics in particular. Physics has a dominant influence on society. It has helped the human being to develop its ideas. Development of digital communication systems rapid mass transport system lasers making bloodless surgeries etc. has made human life easy and pleasant.ul liThere are four fundamental forces in nature that govern the diverse phenomena of the microscopic and macroscopic world. These are the gravitational force the electromagnetic force the strong nuclear force and the weak nuclear force. Unification of forces is a basic quest in physics. The electromagnetic and the weak nuclear forces have now been unified and are seen as aspects of a single electroweak force. Attempts are being made to unify electroweak and the strong force.li liConservation of energy momentum angular momentum charge etc. are considered to be the fundamental laws in physics. Conservation laws have a deep connection with symmetries of nature. Symmetries of space and time and other types of symmetries play a central role in modem theories of fundamental forces in nature.li ulPhysics in Relation to Technology and SocietyliThere are four fundamental forces in nature that govern the diverse phenomena of the microscopic and macroscopic world. These are the gravitational force the electromagnetic force the strong nuclear force and the weak nuclear force. Unification of forces is a basic quest in physics. The electromagnetic and the weak nuclear forces have now been unified and are seen as aspects of a single electroweak force. Attempts are being made to unify electroweak and the strong force.liliConservation of energy momentum angular momentum charge etc. are considered to be the fundamental laws in physics. Conservation laws have a deep connection with symmetries of nature. Symmetries of space and time and other types of symmetries play a central role in modem theories of fundamental forces in nature.liThere are four fundamental forces in nature that govern the diverse phenomena of the microscopic and macroscopic world. These are the gravitational force the electromagnetic force the strong nuclear force and the weak nuclear force. Unification of forces is a basic quest in physics. The electromagnetic and the weak nuclear forces have now been unified and are seen as aspects of a single electroweak force. Attempts are being made to unify electroweak and the strong force.Conservation of energy momentum angular momentum charge etc. are considered to be the fundamental laws in physics. Conservation laws have a deep connection with symmetries of nature. Symmetries of space and time and other types of symmetries play a central role in modem theories of fundamental forces in nature."}, {"id": 12, "question": "Definitions of Fundamental Units", "answer": "Definitions of Fundamental Units"}, {"id": 13, "question": "Absolute Error Relative Error and Percentage Error", "answer": "Absolute Error Relative Error and Percentage Error"}, {"id": 14, "question": "Measurement", "answer": "The process of measurement is basically a comparison process. To measure a physical quantity we have to find out how many times a standard amount of that physical quantity is present in the quantity being measured. The number thus obtained is known as the magnitude and the standard chosen is called the unit of the physical quantity.Measurement"}, {"id": 15, "question": "Unit", "answer": "The unit of a physical quantity is an arbitrarily chosen standard which is widely accepted by the society and in terms of which other quantities of similar nature may be measured.Unit"}, {"id": 16, "question": "Standard", "answer": "The actual physical embodiment of the unit of a physical quantity is known as a standard of that physical quantity. To express any measurement made we need the numerical value n and the unit . Measurement of physical quantity  Numerical value x UnitFor example Length of a rod  8 mwhere 8 is numerical value and m metre is unit of length.Standard"}, {"id": 17, "question": "Fundamental Physical QuantityUnits", "answer": "It is an elementary physical quantity which does not require any other physical quantity to express it. It means it cannot be resolved further in terms of any other physical quantity. It is also known as basic physical quantity.The units of fundamental physical quantities are called fundamental units.For example in M. K. S. system Mass Length and Time expressed in kilogram metre and second respectively are fundamental units.Fundamental Physical QuantityUnits"}, {"id": 18, "question": "Derived Physical QuantityUnits", "answer": "All those physical quantities which can be derived from the combination of two or more fundamental quantities or can be expressed in terms of basic physical quantities are called derived physical quantities.The units of all other physical quantities which car. be obtained from fundamental units are called derived units. For example units of velocity density and force are ms kgm3 kg ms2 respectively and they are examples of derived units.Derived Physical QuantityUnits"}, {"id": 19, "question": "Systems of Units", "answer": "Earlier three different units systems were used in different countries. These were CGS FPS and MKS systems. Nowadays internationally SI system of units is followed. In SI unit system seven quantities are taken as the base quantities.i CGS System. Centimetre Gram and Second are used to express length mass and time respectively.ii FPS System. Foot pound and second are used to express length mass and time respectively.iii MKS System. Length is expressed in metre mass is expressed in kilogram and time is expressed in second. Metre kilogram and second are used to express length mass and time respectively.iv SI Units. Length mass time electric current thermodynamic temperature Amount of substance and luminous intensity are expressed in metre kilogram second ampere kelvin mole and candela respectively.Systems of Units"}, {"id": 20, "question": "Supplementary Units", "answer": "Besides the above mentioned seven unitsthere are two supplementary base units. these are i radian rad for angle and ii steradian sr for solid angle.Supplementary Units"}, {"id": 21, "question": "Advantages of SI Unit System", "answer": "SI Unit System has following advantages over the other Besides the above mentioned seven units there are two supplementary base units. These are systems of unitsi It is internationally acceptedii It is a rational unit systemiii It is a coherent unit systemiv It is a metric systemv It is closely related to CGS and MKS systems of unitsvi Uses decimal system hence is more user friendly.Advantages of SI Unit System"}, {"id": 22, "question": "Other Important Units of Length", "answer": "For measuring large distances e.g. distances of planets and stars etc. some bigger units of length such as astronomical unit light year parsec etc. are used. The average separation between the Earth and the sun is called one astronomical unit.1 AU  1.496 x 10sup11supm. The distance travelled by light in vacuum in one year is called light year.1 light year  9.46 x 10sup15supm. The distance at which an arc of length of one astronomical unit subtends an angle of one second at a point is called parsec.1 parsec  3.08 x 10sup16supm Size of a tiny nucleus  1 fermi  If  10sup15supm Size of a tiny atom  1 angstrom  1A  10sup10supmOther Important Units of Length1115161510"}, {"id": 23, "question": "Parallax Method", "answer": "This method is used to measure the distance of planets and stars from earth.Parallax. Hold a pen in front of your eyes and look at the pen by closing the right eye and  then the left eye. What do you observe The position of the pen changes with respect to the background. This relative shift in the position of the pen object w.r.t. background is called parallax.If a distant object e.g. a planet or a star subtends parallax angle 0 on an arc of radius b known as basis on Earth then distance of that distant object from the basis is given by To estimate size of atoms we can use electron microscope and tunneling microscopy technique. Rutherfords aparticle scattering experiment enables us to estimate size of nuclei of different elements. Pendulum clocks mechanical watches in which vibrations of a balance wheel are used and quartz watches are commonly used to measure time. Cesium atomic clocks can be used to measure time with an accuracy of 1 part in 10sup13supor to a maximum discrepancy of 3 ps in a year. The SI unit of mass is kilogram. While dealing with atoms molecules and subatomic particles we define a unit known as unified atomic mass unit 1 u where 1 u  1.66 x 10sup27supkg.Parallax Method1327"}, {"id": 24, "question": "Estimation of Molecular Size of Oleic Acid", "answer": "For this 1 cmsup3supof oleic acid is dissolved in alcohol to make a solution of 20 cmsup3sup. Then 1 cmsup3supof this solution is taken and diluted to 20 cmsup3sup using alcohol. So the concentration of the solution is as followsAfter that some lycopodium powder is lightly sprinkled on the surface of water in a large trough and one drop of this solution is put in water. The oleic acid drop spreads into a thin large and roughly circular film of molecular thickness on water surface. Then the diameter of the thin film is quickly measured to get its area A. Suppose n drops were put in the water. Initially the approximate volume of each drop is determined V cmsup3sup.Volume of n drops of solution  nV cmsup3supAmount of oleic acid in this solutionThe solution of oleic acid spreads very fast on the surface of water and forms a very thin layer of thickness t. If this spreads to form a film of area A cmsup2sup then thickness of the filmIf we assume that the film has monomolecular thickness this becomes the size or diameter of a molecule of oleic acid. The value of this thickness comes out to be of the order of 10sup9supm.Estimation of Molecular Size of Oleic Acid33333329"}, {"id": 25, "question": "Dimensions", "answer": "The dimensions of a physical quantity are the powers to which the fundamental units of mass length and time must be raised to represent the given physical quantity.Dimensions"}, {"id": 26, "question": "Dimensional Formula", "answer": "The dimensional formula of a physical quantity is an expression telling us how and which of the fundamental quantities enter into the unit of that quantity.It is customary to express the fundamental quantities by a capital letter e.g. length L mass AT time T electric current I temperature K and luminous intensity C. We write appropriate powers of these capital letters within square brackets to get the dimensional formula of any given physical quantity.Dimensional Formula"}, {"id": 27, "question": "Applications of Dimensions", "answer": "The concept of dimensions and dimensional formulae are put to the following usesi Checking the results obtainedii Conversion from one system of units to anotheriii Deriving relationships between physical quantitiesiv Scaling and studying of models.The underlying principle for these uses is the principle of homogeneity of dimensions. According to this principle the net dimensions of the various physical quantities on both sides of a permissible physical relation must be the same also only dimensionally similar quantities can be added to or subtracted from each other.Applications of Dimensions"}, {"id": 28, "question": "Limitations of Dimensional Analysis", "answer": "The method of dimensions has the following limitationsi by this method the value of dimensionless constant cannot be calculated.ii by this method the equation containing trigonometric exponential and logarithmic terms cannot be analyzed.iii if a physical quantity in mechanics depends on more than three factors then relation among them cannot be established because we can have only three equations by equalizing the powers of M L and T.iv it doesnt tell whether the quantity is vector or scalar.Limitations of Dimensional Analysis"}, {"id": 29, "question": "Significant Figures", "answer": "The significant figures are a measure of accuracy of a particular measurement of a physical quantity.Significant figures in a measurement are those digits in a physical quantity that are known reliably plus the first digit which is uncertain.Significant Figures"}, {"id": 30, "question": "The Rules for Determining the Number of Significant Figures", "answer": "i All nonzero digits are significant.ii All zeroes between nonzero digits are significant.iii All zeroes to the right of the last nonzero digit are not significant in numbers without decimal point.iv All zeroes to the right of a decimal point and to the left of a nonzero digit are not significant.v All zeroes to the right of a decimal point and to the right of a nonzero digit are significant.vi In addition and subtraction we should retain the least decimal place among the values operated in the result.vii In multiplication and division we should express the result with the least number of significant figures as associated with the least precise number in operation.viii If scientific notation is not useda For a number greater than 1 without any decimal the trailing zeroes are not significant.b For a number with a decimal the trailing zeros are significant.The Rules for Determining the Number of Significant Figures"}, {"id": 31, "question": "Error", "answer": "The measured value of the physical quantity is usually different from its true value. The result of every measurement by any measuring instrument is an approximate number which contains some uncertainty. This uncertainty is called error. Every calculated quantity which is based on measured values also has an error.Error"}, {"id": 32, "question": "Causes of Errors in Measurement", "answer": "Following are the causes of errors in measurement"}, {"id": 33, "question": "Least Count Error", "answer": "The least count error is the error associated with the resolution of the instrument. Least count may not be sufficiently small. The maximum possible error is equal to the least count."}, {"id": 34, "question": "Instrumental Error", "answer": ". This is due to faulty calibration or change in conditions e.g. thermal expansion of a measuring scale. An instrument may also have a zero error. A correction has to be applied."}, {"id": 35, "question": "Random Error", "answer": "This is also called chance error. It makes to give different results for same measurements taken repeatedly. These errors are assumed to follow the Gaussian law of normal distribution."}, {"id": 36, "question": "Accidental Error", "answer": "This error gives too high or too low results. Measurements involving this error are not included in calculations."}, {"id": 37, "question": "Systematic Error", "answer": "The systematic errors are those errors that tend to be in one direction either positive or negative. Errors due to air buoyancy in weighing and radiation loss in calorimetry are"}, {"id": 38, "question": "systematic errors", "answer": "They can be eliminated by manipulation. Some of the sources of systematic errors arei intrumental errorii imperfection in experimental technique or procedureiii personal errorsCauses of Errors in MeasurementLeast Count Error.Instrumental ErrorRandom Error.Accidental Error.Systematic Error.systematic errors."}, {"id": 39, "question": "Combination of Errors", "answer": "Combination of Errors"}, {"id": 40, "question": "Introduction", "answer": "Motion is one of the significant topics in physics. Everything in the universe moves. It might only be a small amount of movement and veryvery slow but movement does happen. Even if you appear to be standing still the Earth is moving around the sun and the sun is moving around our galaxy.An object is said to be in motion if its position changes with time.The concept of motion is a re live one and a body that may be in motion relative to one reference system may be at rest relative to another.There are two branches in physics that examine the motion of an object.i Kinematics It describes the motion of objects without looking at the cause of the motion.ii Dynamics It relates the motion of objects to the forces which cause them."}, {"id": 41, "question": "Point Object", "answer": "If the length covered by the objects are very large in comparison to the size of the objects the objects are considered point objects."}, {"id": 42, "question": "Reference Systems", "answer": "The motion of a particle is always described with respect to a reference system. A reference system is made by taking an arbitrary point as origin and imagining a coordinate system to be attached to it. This coordinate system chosen for a given problem constitutes the reference system for it. We generally choose a coordinate system attached to the earth as the reference system for most of the problems."}, {"id": 43, "question": "Total Path Length Distance", "answer": "For a particle in motion the total length of the actual path traversed between initial and final positions of the particle is known as the total path length or distance covered by it."}, {"id": 44, "question": "Types of Motion", "answer": "In order to completely describe the motion of an object we need to specify its position. For this we need to know the position coordinates. In some cases three position coordinates are required while in some cases two or one position coordinate is required.Based on these motion can be classified asi One dimensional motion. A particle moving along a straightline or a path is said to undergo one dimensional motion. For example motion of a train along a straight line freely falling body under gravity etc.ii Two dimensional motion. A particle moving in a plane is said to undergo two dimensional motion. For example motion of a shell fired by a gun carrom board coins etc.iii Three dimensional motion. A particle moving in space is said to undergo three dimensional motion. For example motion of a kite in sky motion of aeroplane etc."}, {"id": 45, "question": "Displacement", "answer": "Displacement of a particle in a given time is defined as the change in the position of particle in a particular direction during that time. It is given by a vector drawn from its initial position to its final position."}, {"id": 46, "question": "Factors Distinguishing Displacement from Distance", "answer": " Displacement has direction. Distance does not have direction. The magnitude of displacement can be both positive and negative. Distance is always positive. It never decreases with time. Distance   Displacement "}, {"id": 47, "question": "Uniform Speed and Uniform Velocity", "answer": "Uniform Speed. An object is said to move with uniform speed if it covers equal distances in equal intervals of time howsoever small these intervals of time may be.Uniform Velocity. An object is said to move with uniform velocity if it covers equal displacements in equal intervals of time howsoever small these intervals of time may be."}, {"id": 48, "question": "Variable Speed and Variable Velocity", "answer": "Variable Speed. An object is said to move with variable speed if it covers unequal distances in equal intervals of time howsoever small these intervals of time may be.Variable Velocity. An object is said to move with variable velocity if it covers unequal displacements in equal intervals of time howsoever small these intervals of time may be."}, {"id": 49, "question": "Average Speed and Average Velocity", "answer": "Average Speed. It is the ratio of total path length traversed and the corresponding time interval.OrThe average speed of an object is greater than or equal to the magnitude of the average velocity over a given time interval."}, {"id": 50, "question": "Instantaneous Speed and Instantaneous Velocity", "answer": "Instantaneous Speed. The speed of an object at an instant of time is called instantaneous speed.OrInstantaneous speed is the limit of the average speed as the time interval becomes infinitesimally small.Instantaneous velocityThe instantaneous velocity of a particle is the velocity at any instant of time or at any point of its path.orInstantaneous velocity or simply velocity is defined as the limit of the average velocity as the time interval t becomes infinitesimally small."}, {"id": 51, "question": "Acceleration", "answer": "The rate at which velocity changes is called acceleration."}, {"id": 52, "question": "Uniform Acceleration", "answer": "If an object undergoes equal changes in velocity in equal time intervals it is called uniform acceleration. Average and Instantaneous AccelerationAverage Accelerating. It is the change in the velocity divided by the timeinterval during which the change occurs.Instantaneous Acceleration. It is defined as the limit of the average acceleration as the timeinterval t goes to zero."}, {"id": 53, "question": "Kinematical Graphs", "answer": "The displacementtime and the velocitytime graphs of a particle are often used to provide us with a visual representation of the motion of a particle. The shape of the graphs depends on the initial coordinates and the nature of the acceleration of the particle Fig.The following general results are always validi The slope of the displacementtime graph at any instant gives the speed of the particle at that instant.ii The slope of the velocitytime graph at any instant gives the magnitude of the acceleration of the particle at that instant.iii The area enclosed by the velocitytime graph the timeaxis and the two coordinates at time instants tsub1subto tsub2subgives the distance moved by the particle in the timeinterval from tsub1subto tsub2sub. Equations of Motion for Uniformly Accelerated MotionFor uniformly accelerated motion some simple equations can be derived that relate displacement x time taken f initial velocity u final velocity v and acceleration a. Following equation gives a relation between final and initial velocities v and u of an object moving with uniform acceleration a v  u  at Suppose a body is projected vertically upward from a point A with velocity u.In some problems it is convenient to take the downward direction as positive in such case all the measurements in downward direction are considered as positive i.e. acceleration will be g. But sometimes we may need to take upward as positive and if such case acceleration will be g."}, {"id": 54, "question": "Relative Velocity", "answer": "Relative velocity of an object A with respect to another object B is the time rate at which the object A changes its position with respect to the object B. The relative velocity of two objects moving in the same direction is the difference of the speeds of the objects. The relative velocity of two objects moving in opposite direction is the sum of the speeds of the objects."}, {"id": 55, "question": "Motion", "answer": "in a plane is called as motion in two dimensions e.g. projectile motion circular motion etc. For the analysis of such motion our reference will be made of an origin and two coordinate axes X and Y."}, {"id": 56, "question": "Scalar and Vector Quantities", "answer": "Scalar Quantities. The physical quantities which are completely specified by their magnitude or size alone are called scalar quantities.Examples. Length mass density speed work etc.Vector Quantities. Vector quantities are those physical quantities which are characterised by both magnitude and direction.Examples. Velocity displacement acceleration force momentum torque etc."}, {"id": 57, "question": "Characteristics of Vectors", "answer": "Following are the characteristics of vectorsi These possess both magnitude and direction.ii These do not obey the ordinary laws of Algebra.iii These change if either magnitude or direction or both change.iv These are represented by boldfaced letters or letters having arrow over them."}, {"id": 58, "question": "Unit Vector", "answer": "A unit vector is a vector of unit magnitude and points in a particular direction. It is used to specify the direction only. Unit vector is represented by putting a cap  over the quantity."}, {"id": 59, "question": "Coplanar Vectors", "answer": "Vectors are said to be coplanar if they lie in the same plane or they are parallel to the same plane otherwise they are said to be noncoplanar vectors."}, {"id": 60, "question": "Displacement Vector", "answer": "The displacement vector is a vector which gives the position of a point with reference to a point other than the origin of the coordinate system."}, {"id": 61, "question": "Parallelogram Law of Vector Addition", "answer": "If two vectors acting simultaneously at a point can be represented both in magnitude and direction by the two adjacent sides of a parallelogram drawn from a point then the resultant is represented completely both in magnitude and direction by the diagonal of the parallelogram passing through that point."}, {"id": 62, "question": "Triangle Law of Vector Addition", "answer": "If two vectors are represented both in magnitude and direction by the two sides of a triangle taken in the same order then the resultant of these vectors is represented both in magnitude and direction by the third side of the triangle taken in the opposite order."}, {"id": 63, "question": "Polygon Law of Vector Addition", "answer": "If a number of vectors are represented both in magnitude and direction by the sides of a polygon taken in the same order then the resultant vector is represented both in magnitude and direction by the closing side of the polygon taken in the opposite order."}, {"id": 64, "question": "Properties of Vector Addition", "answer": "Vector addition has following properties"}, {"id": 65, "question": "Resolution of Vectors", "answer": "It is a process of splitting a single vector into two or more vectors in different directions which together produce the same effect as is produced by the single vector alone.The vectors into which the given single vector is splitted are called component of vectors. In fact the resolution of a vector is just opposite to composition of vectors.If the components of a given vector are perpendicular to each other then they are called rectangular components."}, {"id": 66, "question": "Multiplication of Vectors", "answer": "i Scalar product Dot product. Scalar product of two vectors is defined as the product of the magnitude of two vectors with cosine of smaller angle between them."}, {"id": 67, "question": "Lamis Theorem", "answer": "Lamis theorem states If a particle under the simultaneous action of three forces is in equilibrium then each force has a constant ratio with the sine of the angle between the other two forces."}, {"id": 68, "question": "Projectile Motion", "answer": "The projectile is a general name given to an object that is given an initial inclined velocity and which subsequently follows a path determined by the gravitational force acting on it and by the frictional resistance of the air. The path followed by a projectile is called its trajectory.Equation of projectile motion. The general case of projectile motion corresponds to that of an object that has been given an initial velocity u at some angle 8 above or below the horizontal. The horizontal and vertical displacements x and y are given by"}, {"id": 69, "question": "Angular Displacement", "answer": "Angular displacement of the object moving around a circular path is defined as the angle traced out by the radius vector at the centre of the circular path in a given time. angle  arcradius  the magnitude of angular displacement. It is expressed in radians rad."}, {"id": 70, "question": "Angular Velocity", "answer": "Angular velocity of an object in circular motion is defined as the time rate of change of its angular displacement."}, {"id": 71, "question": "Angular Acceleration", "answer": "Angular acceleration of an object in circular motion is defined as the time rate of change of its angular velocity."}, {"id": 72, "question": "Uniform Circular Motion", "answer": "When a body moves in a circular path with a constant speed then the motion of the body is known as uniform circular motion.The time taken by the object to complete one revolution on its circular path is called time period. For circular motion the number of revolutions completed per unit time is known as the frequency v. Unit of frequency is 1 Hertz 1 Hz. It is found that"}, {"id": 73, "question": "Centripetal Acceleration", "answer": "To maintain a particle in its uniform circular motion a radially inward acceleration should be continuously maintained. It is known as the centripetal acceleration."}, {"id": 74, "question": "Dynamics", "answer": "is the branch of physics in which we study the motion of a body by taking into consideration the cause i.e. force which produces the motion."}, {"id": 75, "question": "Force", "answer": "Force is an external cause in the form of push or pull which produces or tries to produce motion in a body at rest or stopstries to stop a moving body or changestries to change the direction of motion of the body. The inherent property with which a body resists any change in its state of motion is called inertia. Heavier the body the inertia is more and lighter the body lesser the inertia. Law of inertia states that a body has the inability to change its state of rest or uniform motion i.e. a motion with constant velocity or direction of motion by itself."}, {"id": 76, "question": "Law 1", "answer": "A body will remain at rest or continue to move with uniform velocity unless an external force is applied to it.First law of motion is also referred to as the Law of inertia. It defines inertia force and inertial frame of reference.I here is always a need of frame of reference to describe and understand the motion of particle lhc simplest frame of reference used are known as the inertial frames.A frame of referent e is known as an inertial frame it within it all accelerations of any particle are caused by the action of real forces on that particle.When we talk about accelerations produced by fictitious or pseudo forces the frame of reference is a noninertial one."}, {"id": 77, "question": "Law 2", "answer": "When an external force is applied to a body of constant mass the force produces an acceleration which is directly proportional to the force and inversely proportional to the mass of the body."}, {"id": 78, "question": "Law 3", "answer": "To every action there is equal and opposite reaction force. When a body A exerts a force on another body B B exerts an equal and opposite force on A."}, {"id": 79, "question": "Linear Momentum", "answer": "The linear momentum of a body is defined as the product of the mass of the body and its velocity."}, {"id": 80, "question": "Impulse", "answer": "Forces acting for short duration are called impulsive forces. Impulse is defined as the product of force and the small time interval for which it acts. It is given byImpulse of a force is a vector quantity and its SI unit is 1 Nm. If force of an impulse is changing with time then the impulse is measured by finding the area bound by forcetime graph for that force. Impulse of a force for a given time is equal to the total change in momentum of the body during the given time. Thus we have"}, {"id": 81, "question": "Law of Conservation of Momentum", "answer": "The total momentum of an isolated system of particles is conserved.In other words when no external force is applied to the system its total momentum remains constant. Recoiling of a gun flight of rockets and jet planes are some simple applications of the law of conservation of linear momentum."}, {"id": 82, "question": "Concurrent Forces and Equilibrium", "answer": "A group of forces which are acting at one point are called concurrent forces.Concurrent forces are said to be in equilibrium if there is no change in the position of rest or the state of uniform motion of the body on which these concurrent forces are acting.For concurrent forces to be in equilibrium their resultant force must be zero. In case of three concurrent forces acting in a plane the body will be in equilibrium if these three forces may be completely represented by three sides of a triangle taken in order. If number of concurrent forces is more than three then these forces must be represented by sides of a closed polygon in order for equilibrium."}, {"id": 83, "question": "i Weight of a body", "answer": "It is the force with which earth attracts a body towards its centre. If M is mass of body and g is acceleration due to gravity weight of the body is Mg in vertically downward direction."}, {"id": 84, "question": "ii Normal Force", "answer": "If two bodies are in contact a contact force arises if the surface is smooth the direction of force is normal to the plane of contact. We call this force as Normal force."}, {"id": 85, "question": "Example", "answer": "Let us consider a book resting on the table. It is acted upon by its weight in vertically downward direction and is at rest. It means there is another force acting on the block in opposite direction which balances its weight. This force is provided by the table and we call it as normal force."}, {"id": 86, "question": "iii Tension in string", "answer": "Suppose a block is hanging from a string. Weight of the block is acting vertically downward but it is not moving hence its weight is balanced by a force due to string. This force is called Tension in string. Tension is a force in a stretched string. Its direction is taken along the string and away from the body under consideration."}, {"id": 87, "question": "Simple Pulley", "answer": "Consider two bodies of masses msub1suband msub2subtied at the ends of an in extensible string which passes over a light and friction less pulley. Let msub1sub msub2sub. The heavier body will move downwards and the lighter will move upwards. Let a be the common acceleration of the system of two bodies which is given by"}, {"id": 88, "question": "Apparent Weight and Actual Weight", "answer": " Apparent weight of a body is equal to its actual weight if the body is either in a state of rest or in a state of uniform motion. Apparent weight of a body for vertically upward accelerated motion is given asApparent weight Actual weight  Ma  M g  a Apparent weight of a body for vertically downward accelerated motion is given asApparent weight  Actual weight Ma  M g  a."}, {"id": 89, "question": "Friction", "answer": "The opposition to any relative motion between two surfaces in contact is referred to as friction. It arises because of the inter meshing of the surface irregularities of the two surfaces in contact."}, {"id": 90, "question": "Static and Dynamic Kinetic Friction", "answer": "The frictional forces between two surfaces in contact i before and ii after a relative motion between them has started are referred to as static and dynamic friction respectively. Static friction is always a little more than dynamic friction.The magnitude of kinetic frictional force is also proportional to normal force."}, {"id": 91, "question": "Limiting Frictional Force", "answer": "This frictional force acts when body is about to move. This is the maximum frictional force that can exist at the contact surface. We calculate its value using laws of friction."}, {"id": 92, "question": "Laws of Friction", "answer": "i The magnitude of limiting frictional force is proportional to the normal force at the contact surface.ii The magnitude of limiting frictional force is independent of area of contact between the surfaces."}, {"id": 93, "question": "Coefficient of Friction", "answer": "The coefficient of friction  between two surfaces is the ratio of their limiting frictional force to the normal force between them i.e."}, {"id": 94, "question": "Angle of Friction", "answer": "It is the angle which the resultant of the force of limiting friction F and the normal reaction R makes with the direction of the normal reaction. If  is the angle of friction we have"}, {"id": 95, "question": "Angle of Repose", "answer": "Angle of repose  is the angle of an inclined plane with the horizontal at which a body placed over it just begins to slide down without any acceleration. Angle of repose is given by   tan1 "}, {"id": 96, "question": "Motion on a Rough Inclined Plane", "answer": "Suppose a motion up the plane takes place under the action of pull P acting parallel to the plane."}, {"id": 97, "question": "Centripetal Force", "answer": "Centripetal force is the force required to move a body uniformly in a circle. This force acts along the radius and towards the centre of the circle. It is given bywhere v is the linear velocity r is the radius of circular path and  is the angular velocity of the body."}, {"id": 98, "question": "Centrifugal Force", "answer": "Centrifugal force is a force that arises when a body is moving actually along a circular path by virtue of tendency of the body to regain its natural straight line path.The magnitude of centrifugal force is same as that of centripetal force."}, {"id": 99, "question": "Motion in a Vertical Circle", "answer": "The motion of a particle in a horizontal circle is different from the motion in vertical circle. In horizontal circle the motion is not effected by the acceleration due to gravity g whereas in the motion of vertical circle the motion is not effected by the acceleration due to gravity g whereas in the motion of vertical circle the value of g plays an important role the motion in this case does not remain uniform. When the particle move up from its lowest position P its speed continuously decreases till it reaches the highest point of its circular path. This is due to the work done against the force of gravity. When the particle moves down the circle its speed would keep on increasing.Let us consider a particle moving in a circular vertical path of radius V and centre o tide with a string. L be the instantaneous position of the particle such thatHere the following forces act on the particle of mass m.i Its weight  mg verticaly downwards.ii The tension in the string T along LO.We can take the horizontal direction at the lowest point p as the position of zero gravitational potential energy. Now as per the principle of conservation of energyFrom this relation we can calculate the tension in the string at the lowest point P midway point and at the highest position of the moving particle."}, {"id": 100, "question": "Case i", "answer": "At the lowest point P   0When the particle completes its motion along the vertical circle it is referred to as Looping the Loop for this the minimum speed at the lowest position must be 5gr"}, {"id": 101, "question": "Energy", "answer": "The energy of a body is its capacity to do work. Anything which is able to do work is said to possess energy. Energy is measured in the same unit as that of work namely Joule.Mechanical energy is of two types Kinetic energy and Potential energy."}, {"id": 102, "question": "Kinetic Energy", "answer": "The energy possessed by a body by virtue of its motion is known as its kinetic energy.For an object of mass m and having a velocity v the kinetic energy is given byK.E. or K  12 mvsub\u00a0subsup2sup"}, {"id": 103, "question": "Potential Energy", "answer": "The energy possessed by a body by virtue of its position or condition is known as its potential energy.There are two common forms of potential energy gravitational and elastic. Gravitational potential energy of a body is the energy possessed by the body by virtue of its position above the surface of the earth.It is given byUP.E.  mghwhere m  mass of a bodyg  acceleration due to gravity on the surface of earth. h  height through which the body is raised. When an elastic body is displaced from its equilibrium position work is needed to be done against the restoring elastic force. The work done is stored up in the body in the form of its elastic potential energy.If an elastic spring is stretched or compressed by a distance Y from its equilibrium position then its elastic potential energy is given byU 12 kxsup2supwhere k  force constant of given spring"}, {"id": 104, "question": "WorkEnergy Theorem", "answer": "According to workenergy theorem the work done by a force on a body is equal to the change in kinetic energy of the body."}, {"id": 105, "question": "The Law of Conservation of Energy", "answer": "According to the law of conservation of energy the total energy of an isolated system does not change. Energy may be transformed from one form to another but the total energy of an isolated system remains constant."}, {"id": 106, "question": "Energy can neither be created nor destroyed", "answer": " Besides mechanical energy the energy may manifest itself in many other forms. Some of these forms are thermal energy electrical energy chemical energy visual light energy nuclear energy etc."}, {"id": 107, "question": "Equivalence of Mass and Energy", "answer": "According to Einstein mass and energy are interconvertible. That is mass can be converted into energy and energy can be converted into mass."}, {"id": 108, "question": "Collision", "answer": "Collision is defined as an isolated event in which two or more colliding bodies exert relatively strong forces on each other for a relatively short time.Collision between particles have been divided broadly into two types.i Elastic collisions ii Inelastic collisions"}, {"id": 109, "question": "Elastic Collision", "answer": "A collision between two particles or bodies is said to be elastic if both the linear momentum and the kinetic energy of the system remain conserved.Example Collisions between atomic particles atoms marble balls and billiard balls."}, {"id": 110, "question": "Inelastic Collision", "answer": "A collision is said to be inelastic if the linear momentum of the system remains conserved but its kinetic energy is not conserved.Example When we drop a ball of wet putty on to the floor then the collision between ball and floor is an inelastic collision. Collision is said to be one dimensional if the colliding particles move along the same straight line path both before as well as after the collision. In one dimensional elastic collision the relative velocity of approach before collision is equal to. the relative velocity of separation after collision."}, {"id": 111, "question": "Coefficient of Restitution or Coefficient of Resilience", "answer": "Coefficient of restitution is defined as the ratio of relative velocity of separation after collision to the relative velocity of approach before collision."}, {"id": 112, "question": "Centre of Mass", "answer": "For a system of particles the centre of mass is defined as that point where the entire mass of the system is imagined to be concentrated for consideration of its translational motion.If all the external forces acting on the bodysystem of bodies were to be applied at the centre of mass the state of rest motion of the bodysystem of bodies shall remain unaffected. The centre of mass of a body or a system is its balancing point. The centre of mass of a two particle system always lies on the line joining the two particles and is somewhere in between the particles."}, {"id": 113, "question": "Motion of centre of Mass", "answer": "The centre of mass of a system of particles moves as if the entire mass of the system were concentrated at the centre of mass and all the external forces were applied at that point. Velocity of centre of mass of a system of two particles msub1suband msub2subwith velocity vsub1suband vsub2subis givenby If no external force acts on the body then the centre of mass will have constant momentum. Its velocity is constant and acceleration is zero i.e. MVsubcmsub constant."}, {"id": 114, "question": "Torque", "answer": "Torque is the moment of force. Torque acting on a particle is defined as the product of the magnitude of the force acting on the particle and the perpendicular distance of the application of force from the axis of rotation of the particle."}, {"id": 115, "question": "Angular Momentum", "answer": "The angular momentum or moment of momentum about an axis of rotation is a vector quantity whose magnitude is equal to the product of the magnitude of momentum and the perpendicular distance of the line of action of momentum from the axis of rotation and its direction is perpendicular to the plane containing the momentum and the perpendicular distance."}, {"id": 116, "question": "Axis of Rotation", "answer": "A rigid body is said to be rotating if every point mass that makes it up describes a circular path of a different radius but the same angular speed. The circular paths of all the point masses have a common centre. A line passing through this common centre is the axis of rotation. A rigid body is said to be in equilibrium if under the action of forcestorques the body remains in its position of rest or of uniform motion.For translational equilibrium the vector sum of all the forces acting on a body must be zero. For rotational equilibrium the vector sum of torques of all the forces acting on that body about the reference point must be zero. For complete equilibrium both these conditions must be fulfilled."}, {"id": 117, "question": "Couple", "answer": "Two equal and opposite forces acting on a body but having different lines of action form a couple. The net force due to a couple is zero but they exert a torque and produce rotational motion."}, {"id": 118, "question": "Moment of Inertia", "answer": "The rotational inertia of a rigid body is referred to as its moment of inertia.The moment of inertia of a body about an axis is defined as the sum of the products of the masses of the particles constituting the body and the square of their respective perpendicular distance from the axis.It is given by ."}, {"id": 119, "question": "Radius of Gyration", "answer": "The distance of a point in a body from the axis of rotation at which if whole of the mass of the body were supposed to be concentrated its moment of inertia about the axis of rotation would be the same as that determined by the actual distribution of mass of the body is called radius of gyration.If we consider that the whole mass of the body is concentrated at a distance K from the axis of rotation then moment of inertia I can be expressed as I  MKsup2sup"}, {"id": 120, "question": "Theorem of Parallel Axes", "answer": "According to this theorem the moment of inertia I of a body about any axis is equal to its moment of inertia about a parallel axis through centre of mass Isubcmsub plus Masup2supwhere M is the mass of the body and V is the perpendicular distance between the axes i.e.I  Isubcmsub Masup2sup"}, {"id": 121, "question": "Theorem of Perpendicular Axes", "answer": "According to this theorem the moment of inertia I of the body about a perpendicular axis is equal to the sum of moments of inertia of the body about two axes at right angles to each other in the plane of the body and intersecting at a point where the perpendicular axis passes i.e."}, {"id": 122, "question": "Rolling Motion", "answer": "The combination of rotational motion and the translational motion of a rigid body is known as rolling motion."}, {"id": 123, "question": "Law of Conservation of Angular Momentum", "answer": "According to the law of conservation of angular momentum if there is no external couple acting the total angular momentum of a rigid body or a system of particles is conserved."}, {"id": 124, "question": "Keplers Laws of Planetary Motion", "answer": "Johannes Kepler formulated three laws which describe planetary motion. They are as followsi Law of orbits. Each planet revolves around the sun in an elliptical orbit with the sun at one of the foci of the ellipse.ii Law of areas. The speed of planet varies in such a way that the radius vector drawn from the sun to planet sweeps out equal areas in equal times."}, {"id": 125, "question": "Newtons Law of Gravitation", "answer": "Newtons law of gravitation states that every particle in the universe attracts every other particle with a force directly proportional to the product of their masses and inversely proportional to the square of the distance between them. The direction of the force is along the line joining the particles. Universal constant of gravitation G is numerically equal to the force of attraction between two particles of unit mass each separated by unit distance. Important Characteristics of Gravitational Forcei Gravitational force between two bodies is a central force i.e. it acts along the line joining the centres of the two interacting bodies.ii Gravitational force between two bodies is independent of the nature of the intervening medium.iii Gravitational force between two bodies does not depend upon the presence of other bodies.iv It is valid for point objects and spherically symmetrical objects.v Magnitude of force is extremely small."}, {"id": 126, "question": "Acceleration Due to Gravity", "answer": "The acceleration produced in a body on account of the force of gravity is known as acceleration due to gravity. It is usually denoted by g. It is always towards the centre of Earth.If a body of mass m lying on the surface of the earth the gravitational force acting on the body is given by"}, {"id": 127, "question": "Mass and Mean Density of Earth", "answer": "Mass and Mean density of Earth is given in the following manner."}, {"id": 128, "question": "Variation of Acceleration Due to Gravity", "answer": "The value of acceleration due to gravity changes with height i.e. altitude depth shape of the earth and rotation of earth about its own axis.a Effect of Altitude. As one goes above the surface of Earth value of acceleration due to gravity gradually goes on decreasing. If gsubhsubbe the value of acceleration due to gravity at a height h from the surface of Earth then"}, {"id": 129, "question": "Gravitational Field", "answer": "The space around a body within which its gravitational force of attraction is experienced by other bodies is called gravitational field."}, {"id": 130, "question": "Intensity of Gravitational Field", "answer": "The intensity of the gravitational field of a body at a point in the field is defined as the force experienced by a body of unit mass placed at that point provided the presence of unit mass does not disturb the original gravitational field."}, {"id": 131, "question": "Gravitational Potential", "answer": "The gravitational potential at a point in the gravitational field of a body is defined as the amount of work done in bringing a body of unit mass from infinity to that point.Gravitational potential at a point situated at a distance r from a body or particle of mass M is given by"}, {"id": 132, "question": "Gravitational Potential Energy", "answer": "The work done in carrying a mass m from infinity to a point at distance r is called gravitational potential energy.The gravitational potential energy of the system is given byi.e. Gravitational potential energy  gravitational potential x mass of the body.It is a scalar quantity and measured in joule."}, {"id": 133, "question": "Escape Velocity", "answer": "The minimum velocity required to project a body vertically upward from the surface of earth so that it comes out of the gravitational field of earth is called escape velocity."}, {"id": 134, "question": "Satellite", "answer": "A satellite is a body which is revolving continuously in an orbit around a comparatively much larger body.The orbit may be either circular or elliptical. A manmade object revolving in an orbit around a planet is called an artificial satellite."}, {"id": 135, "question": "Orbital Velocity", "answer": "Orbital velocity of a satellite is the minimum velocity required to put the satellite into a given orbit around earth."}, {"id": 136, "question": "Geostationary Satellite", "answer": "The satellite having the same time period of revolution as that of the earth is called geostationary satellite. Such satellites should rotate in the equatorial plane from west to east.The orbit of a geostationary satellite is called parking orbit. These satellites are used for communication purposes.A geostationary satellite revolves around the earth in a circular orbit at a height of about 36000 km from the surface of earth."}, {"id": 137, "question": "Inter molecular Force", "answer": "In a solid atoms and molecules are arranged in such a way that each molecule is acted upon by the forces due to the neighbouring molecules. These forces are known as inter molecular forces."}, {"id": 138, "question": "Elasticity", "answer": "The property of the body to regain its original configuration length volume or shape when the deforming forces are removed is called elasticity. The change in the shape or size of a body when external forces act on it is determined by the forces between its atoms or molecules. These short range atomic forces are called elastic forces."}, {"id": 139, "question": "Perfectly elastic body", "answer": "A body which regains its original configuration immediately and completely after the removal of deforming force from it is called perfectly elastic body. Quartz and phospher bronze are the examples of nearly perfectly elastic bodies."}, {"id": 140, "question": "Plasticity", "answer": "The inability of a body to return to its original size and shape even on removal of the deforming force is called plasticity and such a body is called a plastic body."}, {"id": 141, "question": "Stress", "answer": "Stress is defined as the ratio of the internal force F produced when the substance is deformed to the area A over which this force acts. In equilibrium this force is equal in magnitude to the externally applied force. In other words"}, {"id": 142, "question": "Stress is of two types", "answer": "i Normal stress It is defined as the restoring force per unit area perpendicular to the surface of the body. Normal stress is of two types tensile stress and compressive stress.ii Tangential stress When the elastic restoring force or deforming force acts parallel to the surface area the stress is called tangential stress."}, {"id": 143, "question": "Strain", "answer": "It is defined as the ratio of the change in size or shape to the original size or shape. It has no dimensions it is just a number."}, {"id": 144, "question": "Strain is of three types", "answer": "i Longitudinal strain If the deforming force produces a change in length alone the strain produced in the body is called longitudinal strain or tensile strain. It is given asii Volumetric strain If the deforming force produces a change in volume alone the strain produced in the body is called volumetric strain. It is given asiii Shear strain The angle tilt caused in the body due to tangential stress expressed is called shear strain. It is given as The maximum stress to which the body can regain its original status on the removal of the deforming force is called elastic limit."}, {"id": 145, "question": "Hookes Law", "answer": "Hookes law states that within elastic limits the ratio of stress to the corresponding strain produced is a constant. This constant is called the modulus of elasticity. Thus"}, {"id": 146, "question": "Stress Strain Curve", "answer": "Stress strain curves are useful to understand the tensile strength of a given material. The given figure shows a stressstrain curve of a given metal. The curve from O to A is linear. In this region Hookes Proportional limit law is obeyed. In the region from A to 6 stress and strain are not . proportional. Still the body regains its original dimension once the load is removed. Point B in the curve is yield point or elastic limit and the corresponding stress is known as yield strength of the material. The curve beyond B shows the region of plastic deformation. The point D on the curve shows the tensile strength of the material. Beyond this point additional strain leads to fracture in the given material."}, {"id": 147, "question": "Youngs Modulus", "answer": "For a solid in the form of a wire or a thin rod Youngs modulus of elasticity within elastic limit is defined as the ratio of longitudinal stress to longitudinal strain. It is given as"}, {"id": 148, "question": "Bulk Modulus", "answer": "Within elastic limit the bulk modulus is defined as the ratio of longitudinal stress and volumetric strain. It is given as ve indicates that the volume variation and pressure variation always negate each other. Reciprocal of bulk modulus is commonly referred to as the compressibility. It is defined as the fractional change in volume per unit change in pressure."}, {"id": 149, "question": "Shear Modulus or Modulus of Rigidity", "answer": "It is defined as the ratio of the tangential stress to the shear strain.Modulus of rigidity is given by"}, {"id": 150, "question": "Poissons Ratio", "answer": "The ratio of change in diameter D to the original diameter D is called lateral strain. The ratio of change in length l to the original length l is called longitudinal strain. The ratio of lateral strain to the longitudinal strain is called Poissons ratio."}, {"id": 151, "question": "Elastic Fatigue", "answer": "It is the property of an elastic body by virtue of which its behaviour becomes less elastic under the action of repeated alternating deforming forces. Relations between Elastic ModuliFor isotropic materials i.e. materials having the same properties in all directions only two of the three elastic constants are independent. For example Youngs modulus can be expressed in terms of the bulk and shear moduli."}, {"id": 152, "question": "Breaking Stress", "answer": "The ultimate tensile strength of a material is the stress required to break a wire or a rod by pulling on it. The breaking stress of the material is the maximum stress which a material can withstand. Beyond this point breakage occurs.Hence the elastic potential energy of a wire energy density is equal to half the product of its stress and strain."}, {"id": 153, "question": "Pressure", "answer": "The thrust experienced per unit area of the surface of a liquid at rest is called pressure. When a liquid is in equilibrium the force acting on its surface is perpendicular everywhere. The pressure is the same at the same horizontal level. The pressure at any point in the liquid depends on the depth h below the surface density of liquid and acceleration due to gravity."}, {"id": 154, "question": "Pascals Law", "answer": "According to Pascals Law the pressure applied to an enclosed liquid is transmitted undiminished to every portion of the liquid and the walls of the containing vessel. Hydraulic system works on Pascals law. Force exerted to area ratio will be same at all crosssections."}, {"id": 155, "question": "Note", "answer": "A large force is experienced in larger crosssection it a smaller force 4cross is applied in smaller by the relation section. A column of height h of a liquid of density p exerts a pressure P given If Psubasubbe the atmospheric pressure then pressure in a liquid at a depth h from its free surface is given by P  Psubasub hg. Relation is true for incompressible fluids only. The gauge pressure Psubgsub is the difference of the absolute pressure P and the atmospheric pressure Psubasub.Absolute pressure P  Gauge pressure Psubgsub  Atmospheric pressure PsubasubPsubgsubPPsubasub"}, {"id": 156, "question": "Archimedes Principle", "answer": "When a body is partially or completely immersed in a liquid it loses some of its weight. The lossin weight of the body in the liquid is equal to the weight of the liquid displaced by the immersedpart of the body. The upward force excerted by the liquid displaced when a body is immersed is called buoyancy. Due to this there is apparent loss in the weight experienced by the body."}, {"id": 157, "question": "Law of Floatation", "answer": "A body floats in a liquid if weight of the liquid displaced by the immersed portion of the body is equal to the weight of the body.. When a body is immersed partially or wholly in a liquid then the various forces acting on the body arei upward thrust T acting at the centre of buoyancy and whose magnitude is equal to theweight of the liquid displaced and ii the weight of the body W which acts vertically downward through its centre of gravity.a When W  T the body will sink in the liquidb When W  T then the body will remain in equilibrium inside the liquidc When W  T then the body will come upto the surface of the liquid in such a way that the weight of the liquid displaced due to its immersed portion equals the weight of the body. Thus the body will float with only a part of it immersed inside the liquid. The flow of a liquid is said to be steady or stream line flow if such particle of the fluid passingthrough a given point travels along the same path and with same speed as the preceding particle passing through that very point. If the liquid flows over a horizontal surface in the form of layers of different velocities then the flow of the liquid is called laminar flow. The flow of fluid in which velocity of all particles crossing a given point is not same and the motion of fluid becomes irregular or disordered is called turbulent flow."}, {"id": 158, "question": "Equation of Continuity", "answer": "According to equation of continuity if there is no fluid source or sink along the length of a pipe then mass of the fluid crossing any section of the pipe per unit time remains constant. i.e asub1subvsub1subsub1sub asub2subvsub2subsub2subFor incompressible liquids i.e. fluids sub1sub sub2suband hence the equation is given asasub1subvsub1subasub2subvsub2sub It means that speed of flow of liquid is more where the pipe is narrower and speed of flow is lesswhere the crosssection of pipe is more."}, {"id": 159, "question": "Energy of a liquid", "answer": "A liquid can possess three types of energies i kinetic energy ii potential energy and iii pressure energyThe energy possessed by a liquid due to its motion is called kinetic energy i.e. 12mvsup2sup.The potential energy of a liquid of mass m at a height h is given by P.E.  mghThe energy possessed by a liquid by virtue of its pressure is called pressure energy. Pressure energy of liquid in volume dV  PdVPressure energy per unit mass of the liquid"}, {"id": 160, "question": "Bernoullis Theorem", "answer": "For an incompressible nonviscous irrotational liquid having streamlined flow the sum of the pressure energy kinetic energy and potential energy per unit mass is a constant i.e. For steady flow of a nonviscous fluid along a horizontal pipe Bernoullis equation is simplified as"}, {"id": 161, "question": "Viscosity", "answer": "Viscosity is the property of the fluid liquid or gas by virtue of which an internal frictional force comes into play when the fluid is in motion in the form of layers having relative motion. It opposes the relative motion of the different layers. Viscosity is also called as fluid friction. The viscous force directly depends on the area of the layer and the velocity gradient."}, {"id": 162, "question": "Coefficient of Viscosity", "answer": "Coefficient of viscosity of a liquid is equal to the tangential force required to maintain a unit velocity gradient between two parallel layers of liquid each of area unity.The SI unit of coefficient of viscosity is poiseuille Pl or Pa  s or Nmsup2sups or kg msup1supssup1sup. Dimensional formula of q is MLsup1supTsup1sup."}, {"id": 163, "question": "Stokes Law", "answer": "According to Stokes law the backward dragging force acting on a small spherical body of radius r moving with a velocity v through a viscous medius of coefficient of viscosity \u00a0is given byF  6r"}, {"id": 164, "question": "Terminal Velocity", "answer": "It is maximum constant velocity acquired by the body while falling freely in a viscous medium. This is attained when the apparent weight is compensated by the viscous force.It is given bywhere p be the density of the material of the body of radius r and o be the density of the medium."}, {"id": 165, "question": "Poiseuilles Equation", "answer": "According to Poiseuille if a pressure difference P is maintained across the two ends of a capillary tube of length l and radius r then the volume of liquid coming out of the tube per second is directly proportional to the pressure difference P.ii directly proportional to the fourth power of radius r of the capillary tube.iii inversely proportional to the coefficient of viscosity  of the liquid.iv inversely proportional to the length i of the capillary tube.It is given as"}, {"id": 166, "question": "Reynolds Number", "answer": "Reynold number Re is a dimensionless number whose value gives an approximate idea whether the flow of a fluid will be streamline or turbulent. It is given bywhere p  density of fluid flowing with a speed u d stands for the diameter of the pipe and q is the viscosity of the fluid. Value of Re remains same in any system of units. It is observed that flow is streamline or laminar for Rsube\u00a0sub 1000 and the flow is turbulent for Rsube\u00a0sub 2000. The flow becomes unsteady for Rsube\u00a0subbetween 1000 and 2000. The critical value of Rsube\u00a0sub at which turbulence sets is same for the geometrically similar flows. Rsube\u00a0submay also be expressed as the ratio of inertial force force due to inertia i.e. mass of moving fluid or due to inertia of obstacle in its path to viscous force i.e."}, {"id": 167, "question": "Critical Velocity", "answer": "The critical velocity is that velocity of liquid flow upto which its flow is streamline and above which its flow becomes turbulent.It is given bywhere K is a dimensionless constant q is coefficient of viscosity of liquid p is density of liquid and r is the radius of tube."}, {"id": 168, "question": "Surface Tension", "answer": "It is the property of the liquid by virtue of which the free surface of liquid at rest tends to have minimum area and as such it behaves as a stretched elastic membrane. The force acting per unit length of line drawn on the liquid surface and normal to it parallel to the surface is called the force of surface tension.It is given byThe SI unit of surface tension is Nmsup1\u00a0supand its dimensional formula is MTsup2sup"}, {"id": 169, "question": "Surface Energy", "answer": "Energy possessed by the surface of the liquid is called surface energy. Change in surface energy is the product of surface tension and change in surface area under constant temperature. The height to which water rises in a capillary tube of radius r is given bywhere T is the surface tension of the liquid and 0 is the angle of contact.Due to surface tension there is excess pressure on the concave side of a surface film of a liquid overthe convex side and is equal to 2Tr . For a soap bubble the excess pressure is 4Tr where r denotes the radius of the surface."}, {"id": 170, "question": "Angle of Contact", "answer": "The angle which the tangent to the liquid surface at the point of contact makes with the solid surface inside the liquid is called angle of contact. Intermolecular force amongst molecules of the same material is called the force of cohesion. However force amongst molecules of different materials is called the force of adhesion."}, {"id": 171, "question": "Torricellis Theorem", "answer": "According to this theorem velocity of efflux i.e. the velocity with which the liquid flows out of on orifice i.e. a narrow hole is equal to that which a freely falling body would acquire in falling through a vertical distance equal to the depth of orifice below the free surface of liquid.The velocity is given byV  2gh"}, {"id": 172, "question": "Thermal Expansion", "answer": "The increase of size of a body due to the increase in the temperature is called thermal expansion. Three types of expansions can take place in solids viz. linear superficial and volume expansioni"}, {"id": 173, "question": "Linear Expansion", "answer": "The increase in the length of a solid on heating is called linear expansion.If the temperature of a rod of original length l is raised by a small amount t its length increases by l. Then the linear expansion is given byl  l  twhere a is the coefficient of linear expansion of the given solid. The unit of \u00a0is per degree Celsius Csup1sup in the CGS and per kelvin Ksup1sup in the SI system.ii"}, {"id": 174, "question": "Superficial or Area Expansion", "answer": "The increase in surface area of the solid on heating is called superficial expansion.If Asub0subis the area of a solid at 0C and A its area at tC then Asubtsub Asub0subl  twhere \u00a0is known as the coefficient of superficial expansion. Unit of \u00a0is Csup1supor Ksup1sup.iii"}, {"id": 175, "question": "Volume Expansion", "answer": "The increase in volume of the solid on heating is called volume expansion.The change in the volume of a solid with a change in temperature t\u00a0is given by v\u00a0 Vsub\u00a0subtwhere y is the coefficient of volume expansion. The relation among coefficients of linear expansion  superficial expansion  and volume expansion  is given as For a given solid the three coefficients of expansion span stylefontfamily Calibri sansserifspan stylefontsize small\u00a0  spanspan \u00a0are not constant. Their values depend on the temperature range. Liquids have volume expansion only. If we do not take into account the expansion of solid container then the expansion of liquid is called apparent expansion. On the other hand if we take into account the expansion of solid too it is referred as the real expansion of liquid. It is found that subrsub subasub subgsub where subrsub real expansion coefficient of liquid subasub apparent expansion coefficient of liquid and subgsub volume expansion coefficient of container vessel glass. Water exhibits an anomalous behaviour. It contracts on heating between 0 C and 4 C but expands on heating beyond 4 C. Thus specific volume of water is minimum at 4 C or density of water is maximum at 4 C. This property of water has an important environmental effect."}, {"id": 176, "question": "Thermal Stress", "answer": "When a rod is held between two fixed supports and its temperature is increased the fixed supports do not allow the rod to expand which results in a stress which is called thermal stress.Thermal stress in the rod is given bywhere Y is the Youngs modulus for the material of the rod A is the area crosssection of the rod a is the coefficient of linear expansion and F is the developed force in the rod."}, {"id": 177, "question": "Thermal Capacity", "answer": "The thermal capacity of a body is the quantity of heat required to raise the temperature of the whole of the body through a unit degree. It is measured in calorie per C or joule per K.If Q be the amount of heat needed to produce a change in temperature t of the substance then thermal capacity of the substance is given byDimensional formula of heat capacity is MLsup2supTsup2supKsup1sup"}, {"id": 178, "question": "Specific Heat Capacity", "answer": "The specific heat capacity also referred to as specific heat of a substance is the amount of heat required to raise the temperature of a unit mass of substance through 1 C. It is measured in cal gsup1supCsup1supor J kgsup1supKsup1sup.The specific heat capacity of a substance is given bywhere m is mass of substance and Q is the heat required to change its temperature t. Molar specific heat capacity of a substance is defined as the amount of heat required to raise the temperature of 1 mole of the substance by 1C.It is given byThe unit of molar specific heat capacity is J molesup1supKsup1supin SI system and Cal molsup1supCsup1\u00a0supin CGS system.The dimensional formula of molar specific heat capacity is MLsup2supTsup2supKsup1supmolesup1sup."}, {"id": 179, "question": "Calorimetry", "answer": "Calorimetry is concerned with the measurement of heat the basic apparatus for this purpose being called the calorimeter.When two bodies at different temperatures are mixed heat flows from the body at a higher temperature to the one at a lower temperature until a common equilibrium temperature is reached. Assuming this heat exchange to be confined to the two bodies alone i.e neglecting any heat loss to the surroundings we have from the law of energy conservationHeat gained by one body  heat lost by the other. Transition of matter from one state solid liquid and gas to another is called a change of state. The change of state from solid to liquid is called melting and from liquid to solid is called fusion. It is observed that the temperature remains constant until the entire amount of the solid substance melts i.e. both the solid and liquid states of the substance coexist in thermal equilibrium during the change of state from solid to liquid. The temperature at which a solid melts is called its melting point. The value of melting point of a solid is characteristic of the substance and depends on pressure also. Melting of ice under increased pressure and refreezing on reducing the pressure is called regelation. The change of state from liquid to vapour or gas is called vaporisation. The temperature at which the liquid and vapour states of a substance coexist is called its boiling point. The change from solid state to vapour state without passing through the liquid state is called sublimation."}, {"id": 180, "question": "The Basic Heat Formula", "answer": "The heat Q required to raise the temperature of a mass m of a substance of specific heat capacity s through t degrees is given byi.e. Heat required  mass x specific heat x change in temperature"}, {"id": 181, "question": "Latent Heat", "answer": "Latent heat of a substance is the amount of heat energy required to change the state of unit mass of the substance from solid to liquid or from liquid to gasvapour without any change in temperature. The latent heat of fusion Lsubfsub is the heat per unit mass required to change a substance from solid into liquid at the same temperature and pressure. The latent heat of vaporisation Lsubvsub is the heat per unit mass required to change a substance from liquid to vapour state without change in temperature and pressure."}, {"id": 182, "question": "Heat Transfer", "answer": "Heat can be transferred from one place to another by three different methods namely conduction convection and radiation. Conduction usually takes place in solids convection in liquids and gases and no medium is required for radiation.i Conduction According to Maxwell conduction is the flow of heat through an unequally heated body from places of higher temperature to those of lower temperature. Rate of heat transfer is given bywhere K is called Thermal Conductivity and A is area of crosssection.ii Convection Maxwell defines convection as the flow of heat by the motion of the hot body itself carrying its heat with it.iii Radiation Radiation is the mode of heat transfer in which heat travels directly from one place to another without the agency of any intervening medium. Thermal conductivity is defined as heat energy transferred in unit time from unit area having a unit difference in temperature over unit length. It is expressed in Jssup1supmsup1\u00a0supCsup1supor Wsup1supKsup1sup"}, {"id": 183, "question": "Thermal Resistance", "answer": "The thermal resistance of a body is a measure of its opposition to the flow of heat through it. It is defined as"}, {"id": 184, "question": "Newtons Law of Cooling", "answer": "Newtons law of cooling states that the rate of loss of heat of a body is directly proportional to the difference in temperature of the body and the surroundings provided the difference in temperature is small not more than 40 C. ve sign implies that as time passes temperature T decreases.When an object at temperature Tsub1subis placed in a surrounding of temperature Tsub2subthe net energyradiated per second is"}, {"id": 185, "question": "Black Body Radiation", "answer": "i"}, {"id": 186, "question": "Emissive Power", "answer": "The amount of heat energy rediated per unit area of the surface of a body per unit time and per unit wavelength range is constant which is called as the emissive power esubsub of the given surface given temperature and wavelength. Its S.I. unit is Jssup1supmsup2 sup.ii"}, {"id": 187, "question": "Absorptive Power", "answer": "When any radiation is incident over a surface of a body a part of it gets reflected a part of it gets refracted and the rest of it is absorbed by that surface. Therefore the absorptive power of a surface at a given temperature and for a given wavelength is the ratio of the heat energy absorbed by a surface to the total energy incident on it at a certain time. It is represented by asubsub. It has no unit as it is a ratio.iii"}, {"id": 188, "question": "Perfect Black Body", "answer": "A body is said to be a perfect black body is its absorptivity is 1. It neither reflects nor transmits but absorbs all the thermal radiations incident on it irrespetive of their wavelengths.iv"}, {"id": 189, "question": "Weins Displacement Law", "answer": "This law states that as the temperature increases the maximum value of the radiant energy emitted by the black body move towards shorter wavelengths. Wein found that The product of the peak wavelength \u00a0submsub and the Kelvin temperature T of the black body should remain constant. \u00a0subm\u00a0subx T bWhere b is constant known as Weins constant. Its value is 2.898 x 10sup3supmk.v"}, {"id": 190, "question": "Thermal Equilibrium", "answer": "A thermodynamic system is in an equilibrium state if the macroscopic variables such as pressure volume temperature mass composition etc. that characterise the system do not change in time. In thermal equilibrium the temperature of the two systems are equal."}, {"id": 191, "question": "Zeroth Law of Thermodynamics", "answer": "This law identifies thermal equilibrium and introduces temperature as a tool for identifying f equilibrium. According to this law If two systems are in thermal equilibrium with a third system then those two systems themselves are in equilibrium."}, {"id": 192, "question": "Heat Work and Internal Energy", "answer": " Energy that is transferred between a system and its surroundings whenever there is temperature difference between the system and its surroundings is called heat. Work is said to be done if a body or a system moves through a certain distance in the direction of the applied force. It is given asdW  PdVwhere P is the pressure of the gas in the cylinder. If we consider a bulk system consisting of a large number of molecules then internal energy  of the system is the sum of the kinetic energies and potential energies of these molecules.This energy is possessed by a system due to its molecular motion and molecular configuration. The internal energy is denoted by U.U  Esubksub Esubpsubwhere Esubksuband Esubpsubrepresent the kinetic and potential energies of the molecules of the system. Internal energy of a system is a macroscopic variable and it depends only on the state of the system. Its value depends only on the given state of the system and does not depend on the path taken to arrive that state."}, {"id": 193, "question": "First Law of Thermodynamics", "answer": "The first law of thermodynamics is simply the general law of conservation of energy applied to any system. According to this law the total heat energy change in any system is the sum of the internal energy change and the work done.When a certain quantity of heat dQ is subjected to a system a part of it is used in increasing the internal energy by dU and a part is used in performing external work dW hencedQ  dU  dW For gases the specific heat capacity depends on the process or the conditions under which heat capacity transfer takes place. There are mainly two principal specific heat capacities for a gas. These are specific heat capacity at constant volume and specific heat capacity at constant pressure. From First Law of Thermodynamics we find a relation between two principal specific heats of an ideal gas. According to the relationCsubpsubCsubsub RHere Csubpsuband Csubsubare molar specific heats under constant pressure and constant volume condition respectively.The specific heat capacity of a gas at constant pressure is greater than the specific heat capacity of the gas at constant volume i.e. Csubpsub Csubsub. Reason is that when heat supplied to a gas at constant volume no work would be done by the gas against the external pressure and all the energy is used to raise the temperature of the gas. On the other hand when the heat is supplied to the gas at constant pressure its volume increases and the heat energy supplied to it is used to increase the temperature of the gas as well as in doing the work against the external pressure.The difference between the two specific heats is the thermal equivalent of the work done in expanding the gas against the external pressure."}, {"id": 194, "question": "Expression for the Relation between Cp and C", "answer": "Let P V and T be the pressure volume and absolute temperature initially of one mole of an ideal gas.Case i The heat dQ is supplied to the gas at constant volume so that the temperature increases to T  dT."}, {"id": 195, "question": "Thermodynamic State Variables", "answer": "Thermodynamic state variables of a system are the parameters which describe equilibrium states of the system. For example equilibrium state of gas is completely specified by the values of pressure volume temperature mass and composition."}, {"id": 196, "question": "Equation of State", "answer": "The equation of state represents the connection between the state variables of a system. For example the those equation of state of an idealperfect gas in represented asPV  RTwhere g is number of moles of the gas and R is gas constant for one mole of the gas. Thermodynamic state variables are of two kinds extensive and intensive. Extensive variables indicate the size of the system but intensive variables do not indicate the size. Volume mass internal energy of a system are extensive variables but pressure temperature and density are intensive variables."}, {"id": 197, "question": "Thermodynamic Processes", "answer": "Any process in which the thermodynamic variables of a thermodynamic system change is known as thermodynamic process."}, {"id": 198, "question": "QuasiStatic Processes", "answer": "Processes that are sufficiently slow and do not involve accelerated motion of piston andor large temperature gradient are quasistatic processes.In this process the change in pressure or change in volume or change in temperature of the system is very small."}, {"id": 199, "question": "Isothermal Process", "answer": "A change in pressure and volume of a gas without any change in its temperature is called an isothermal change. In such a change there is a free exchange of heat between the gas and its surroundings."}, {"id": 200, "question": "Adiabatic Process", "answer": "A process in which no exchange of heat energy takes place between the gas and the surroundings is called an adiabatic process. The work done dW under isothermal change is given by"}, {"id": 201, "question": "PV Diagram", "answer": "A graph representing the variation of pressure with the variation of volume is called PV diagram. The work done by the thermodynamic system is equal to the area under PV diagram. It is given as"}, {"id": 202, "question": "Reversible Process", "answer": "A process which can retrace so that the system passes through the same states is called a reversible process otherwise it is irreversible.Irreversibility arises mainly from two causesi Many processes like free expansion or an explosive chemical reaction take the system to nonequilibrium states.ii Most processes involve friction viscosity and other dissipative effects."}, {"id": 203, "question": "Second Law of Thermodynamics", "answer": "This principle which disallows certain phenomena consistent with the First law of thermodynamics is known as the second law of thermodynamics.Following are the two statements of second law of thermodynamics.KelvinPlanck Statement It is impossible to construct an engine operating in a cycle to extractheat from hot body and convert it completely into work without leaving any change anywhere i.e. 100 conversion of heat into work is impossible.Clausius Statement It is impossible for a self acting machine operating in a cycle unaided by any external energy to transfer heat from a cold body to a hot body. In other words heat can not flow itself from a colder body to a hotter body. A heat engine is a device by which a system is made to undergo a cyclic process that resultsin conversion of heat to work. Basically a heat engine consists of i a heat source ii a heat sink and iii a working substance. Carnots Engine. He proposed a hypothetical engine working on a cyclicreversible process operating between two temperatures. Its efficiency is independent of the working substance and is given by 1Tsub2subTsub1subwhere Tsub1subis the temperature of source and Tsub2subis the temperature of sink. According to Carnots theorem a working between two given temperatures Tsub1suband Tsub2subof the hot and cold reservoirs respectively no engine can have efficiency more than that of Carnots engine and b the efficiency of the Carnot engine is independent of the nature of the working substance."}, {"id": 204, "question": "Refrigerator", "answer": "The process of removing heat from bodies colder than their surroundings is called refrigeration and the device doing so is called refrigerator.In the refrigerator heat is absorbed at low temperature and rejected at higher temperature with the help of external mechanical work. Thus a refrigerator is a heat engine working backward and hence it is also called heat pump.Refrigerator works on the reverse process of Carnot engine. By the work done on the system heat is extracted from low temperature sink Tsub2suband passed on to high temperature source Tsub1sub. The coefficient of performance is given by"}, {"id": 205, "question": "Ideal Gas", "answer": "An ideal gas or a perfect gas is that gas which strictly obeys gas laws such as Boyles law Charles law Gay Lussacs law etc.An ideal gas has following characteristicsi Molecule of an ideal gas is a point mass with no geometrical dimensions.ii There is no force of attraction or repulsion amongst the molecules of the gas."}, {"id": 206, "question": "Kinetic Theory and Gas Pressure", "answer": "The pressure of a gas is the result of continuous bombardment of the gas molecules against the walls of the container. According to the kinetic theory the pressure P exerted by an ideal gas is given by"}, {"id": 207, "question": "Boyles Law", "answer": "According to this law the volume V of a fixed mass of a gas is inversely proportional to the pressure P of the gas provided temperature of the gas is kept constant."}, {"id": 208, "question": "Charles Law", "answer": "According to this law the volume V of a given mass of a gas is directly proportional to thetemperature of the gas provided pressure of the gas remains constant."}, {"id": 209, "question": "Gay Lussacs Law or Pressure Law", "answer": "According to this law the pressure P of a given mass of a gas is directly proportional to its absolute temperature T provided the volume V of the gas remains constant."}, {"id": 210, "question": "Equation of State of an Ideal Gas", "answer": "The relationship between pressure P volume V and absolute temperature T of a gas is called its equation of state. The equation of state of an ideal gasPV  nRTwhere n is the number of moles of the enclosed gas and R is the molar gas constant which is the same for all gases and its value isR  8.315 JKsup1supmobsup1sup"}, {"id": 211, "question": "Avagadros Law", "answer": "Equal volumes of all gases under S.T.P. contain the same number of molecules equalling 6.023 x 10sup23sup."}, {"id": 212, "question": "Grahams Law of Diffusion of Gases", "answer": "It states that rate of diffusion of a gas is inversely proportional to the square root of the density of the gas.Hence denser the gas the slower is the rate of diffusion."}, {"id": 213, "question": "Daltons Law of Partial Pressures", "answer": "According to this law the resultant pressure exerted by a mixture of noninteracting gases is equalto the sum of their individual pressures.ie. P  Psub1sub Psub2sub Psubnsub Mean or average speed of molecules of a gas is defined as the arithmetic mean of the speeds of gas molecules. Root mean square speed of gas molecules is defined as the square root of the mean of the squares of the speeds of gas molecules. Most probable speed of gas molecules is defined as the speed which is possessed by maximum number of molecules in a gas"}, {"id": 214, "question": "Kinetic Interpretation of Temperature", "answer": "The total average kinetic energy of all the molecules of a gas is proportional to its absolute temperature T. Thus the temperature of a gas is a measure of the average kinetic energy IT of the molecules of the gas.U  32 RTAccording to this interpretation of temperature the average kinetic energy U is zero at T  0 i.e. the motion of molecules ceases altogether at absolute zero."}, {"id": 215, "question": "Degrees of Freedom", "answer": "The total number of independent coordinates required to specify the position of a molecule or the number of independent modes of motion possible with any molecule is called degree of freedom.Mono di and polyatomic N molecules have 35 or 3 NK number of degrees of freedom where K is the number of constraints restrictions associated with the structure."}, {"id": 216, "question": "Law of Equipartition of Energy", "answer": "For a dynamic system in thermal equilibrium the energy of the system is equally distributed amongst the various degrees of freedom and the energy associated with each degree of freedom per molecule is 12 kT where k is Boltzman constant."}, {"id": 217, "question": "Mean Free Path", "answer": "Mean free path of a molecule in a gas is the average distance travelled by the molecule between two successive collisionsi Smaller the number of molecules per unit volume of the gas larger is the mean free path.ii Smaller the diameter larger is the mean free path.iii Smaller the density larger is the mean free path. In the case of vacuum   0  iv Smaller the pressure of a gas larger is the mean free path.v Higher the temperature of a gas larger is the mean free path."}, {"id": 218, "question": "Periodic Motion", "answer": "Motions processes or phenomena which repeat themselves at regular intervals are called periodic."}, {"id": 219, "question": "Oscillatory Motion", "answer": "The motion of a body is said to be oscillatory motion if it moves to and fro about a fixed point after regular intervals of time. The fixed point about which the body oscillates is called mean position or equilibrium position."}, {"id": 220, "question": "Simple Harmonic Motion", "answer": "Simple harmonic motion is a special type of periodic oscillatory motion in whichi The particle oscillates on a straight lineii The acceleration of the particle is always directed towards a fixed point on the line.iii The magnitude of acceleration is proportional to the displacement of the particle from the"}, {"id": 221, "question": "Characteristics of SHM", "answer": "The displacement x in SHM at time t is given byx  A sin t  where the three constants A  and  characterize the SHM i.e. they distinguish one SHM from another. A SHM can also be described by a cosine function as followsx  A cos t   The displacement of an oscillating particle at any instant is equal to the change in its position vector during that time. The maximum value of displacement in an oscillatory motion on either side of its mean position is called displacement amplitude or simple amplitude.Thus amplitude A  x max. The time taken by an oscillating particle to complete one full oscillation to and fro about its mean equilibrium position is called the time period of SHM. It is given by"}, {"id": 222, "question": "Frequency", "answer": "The number of vibrations made by a particle in one second is called Frequency. It is represented by v. Its unit is hertz Hz v 1T"}, {"id": 223, "question": "Phase", "answer": "The quantity t  is called the phase of SHM at time t it describes the state of motion at that instant. The quantity  is the phase at time f  0 and is called the phase constant or initial phase or epoch of the SHM. The phase constant is the timeindependent term in the cosine or sine function. The force responsible for maintaining the S.H.M. is called restoring force.If the displacement x from the equilibrium position is small the restoring force F acting on the body is given byF  kxwhere k is a force constant. Energy in S.H.M.When a body executes SHM its energy changes between kinetic and potential but the total energy is always constant. At any displacement x from the equilibrium position"}, {"id": 224, "question": "Springs in Series", "answer": "If two springs having spring constant ksub1suband ksub2sub are joined in series the spring constant of the combination is given by"}, {"id": 225, "question": "Springs in Parallel", "answer": "If two springs having spring constants ksub1suband ksub2sub are joined in parallel the spring constant of the combination is given byk  ksub1sub ksub2sub When one spring is attached to two masses msub1suband msub2sub then"}, {"id": 226, "question": "Simple Pendulum", "answer": "A simple pendulum is the most common example of bodies executing S.H.M. An ideal simple pendulum consists of a heavy point mass body suspended by a weightless in extensible and perfectly flexible string from a rigid support about which it is free to oscillate. The time period of simple pendulum of length l is given byThe time period of a simple pendulum depends oni length of the pendulum andii the acceleration due to gravity g. A seconds pendulum is a pendulum whose time period is. 2s. At a place where g  9.8 mssup2sup the length of a seconds pendulum is found to be 99.3 cm  1 m. If a liquid of density p oscillates in a vertical Utube of uniform cross sectional area A then the time period of oscillation is given by If a cylinder of mass m length L density of material p and uniform area of cross section A oscillates vertically in a liquid of density o then the time period of oscillation is given by"}, {"id": 227, "question": "Undamped Simple Harmonic oscillations", "answer": "When a simple harmonic system oscillates with a constant amplitude which does not change with time its oscillations are called undamped simple harmonic oscillations."}, {"id": 228, "question": "Damped Simple Harmonic oscillations", "answer": "When a simple harmonic system oscillates with a decreasing amplitude with time its oscillations are called damped simple harmonic oscillations.The angular frequency of the damped oscillator is given by A system is said to execute free oscillations if on being displaced or disturbed from its position of equilibrium it oscillates itself without outside interference.When a system is compelled to oscillate with a frequency other than its natural frequency it is said to execute forced oscillations.The external force which causes forced oscillation is of sinusoidal nature. It is given as Resonance is the phenomenon of setting a body into oscillations with large amplitude under the influence of some external periodic force whose frequency is exactly equal to the natural frequency of the given body. Such oscillations are called the resonant oscillations. The two or more oscillations linked together in such a way that the exchange of energy takes place between them are called coupled oscillators. The oscillations produced by coupled oscillators are known as coupled oscillations. The speed of a mechanic wave depends upon the properties of the medium in which it is travelling. If E is the elastic constant and  is the density of the medium then the speed of the wave is given by In case of electric magnetic waves we know that they are the combinations of the oscillation of electric and magnetic fields in perpendicular directions. Their speed of propagation depends upon the permitivity and the permeability of the medium. If sub0subis permeability and sub0subis the permitivity of the medium in vaccum then"}, {"id": 229, "question": "Waves", "answer": "Wave is a form of disturbance which travels through a material medium due to the repeated f periodic motion of the particles of the medium about their mean positions without any actualtransportation of matter."}, {"id": 230, "question": "Characteristics of wave", "answer": "The characteristics of waves are as followsi The particles of the medium traversed by a wave execute relatively small vibrations about their mean positions but the particles are not permanently displaced in the direction of propagation of the wave.ii Each successive particle of the medium executes a motion quite similar to its predecessors alongperpendicular to the line of travel of the wave.iii During wave motion only transfer of energy takes place but not that of a portion of the medium.Waves are mainly of three types a mechanical or elastic waves b electromagnetic waves and c matter waves."}, {"id": 231, "question": "Mechanical waves", "answer": "Mechanical waves can be produced or propagated only in a material medium. These waves are governed by Newtons laws of motion. For example waves on water surface waves on strings sound waves etc."}, {"id": 232, "question": "Electromagnetic Waves", "answer": "These are the waves which require no material medium for their production and propagation i.e. they can pass through vacuum and any other material medium. Common examples of electromagneticwaves are visible light ultraviolet light radiowaves microwaves etc."}, {"id": 233, "question": "Matter waves", "answer": "These waves are associated with moving particles of matter like electrons protons neutrons etc. Mechanical waves are of two typesi Transverse wave motion ii Longitudinal wave motion"}, {"id": 234, "question": "Transverse wave motion", "answer": "In transverse waves the particles of the medium vibrate at right angles to the direction in which the wave propagates. Waves on strings surface water waves and electromagnetic waves are transverse waves. In electromagnetic waves which include light waves the disturbance that travels is not a result of vibrations of particles but it is the oscillation of electric and magnetic fields which takes place at right angles to the direction in which the wave travels."}, {"id": 235, "question": "Longitudinal wave motion", "answer": "In these types of waves particles of the medium vibrate to and fro about their mean position along the direction of propagation of energy. These are also called pressure waves. Sound waves are longitudinal mechanical waves."}, {"id": 236, "question": "Wavelength", "answer": "The distance travelled by the disturbance during the time of one vibration by a medium particle is called the wavelength . In case of a transverse wave the wavelength may also be defined as the distance between two successive crests or troughs. In case of a longitudinal wave the wavelength  is equal to distance from centre of one compression or refraction to another."}, {"id": 237, "question": "Wave Velocity", "answer": "Wave velocity is the time rate of propagation of wave motion in the given medium. It is different from particle velocity. Wave velocity depends upon the nature of medium.Wave velocity   frequency v x wavelength "}, {"id": 238, "question": "Amplitude", "answer": "The amplitude of a wave is the maximum displacement of the particles of the medium from their mean position."}, {"id": 239, "question": "Time Period", "answer": "The time taken by a particle to complete one vibration is called time period.T  1v it is expressed in seconds. The velocity of transverse waves in a stretched string is given bywhere T is the tension in the string and  is the mass per unit length of the string  is also called linear mass density of the string. SI unit of  is kg m1. The velocity of the longitudinal wave in an elastic medium is given bywhere E is the modulus of elasticity of the medium and  is the density of the medium. In case of solids E is Youngs modulus of elasticity Y then"}, {"id": 240, "question": "Newtons Formula for the velocity of sound in Air", "answer": "According to Newton when sound waves travel in air or in a gaseous media the change is taking place isothermally and hence it is found thatSpeed of sound in air at STP conditions calculated on the basis of Newtons formula is 280 mssup1sup. However the experimentally determined values is 332 mssup1sup.According to Laplace during propagation of sound waves the change takes place under adiabatic conditions because gases are thermal insulators and compressions and refractions are alternately taking place with a high frequency."}, {"id": 241, "question": "Factors Influencing Velocity of Sound", "answer": "The velocity of sound in any gaseous medium is affected by a large number of factors like density pressure temperature humidity wind velocity etc.i The velocity of sound in a gas is inversely proportional to the square root of density of the gas.ii The velocity of sound is independent of the change in pressure of the gas provided temperature remains constant.iii The velocity of sound in a gas is directly proportional to the square root of its absolute temperature.iv The velocity of sound in moist air is greater than the velocity of sound in dry air.v If wind flows at an angle  to the direction of propagation of sound the velocity of sound is v  w cos  where w is the velocity of wind."}, {"id": 242, "question": "General Equation of Progressive Waves", "answer": "A progressive wave is one which travels in a given direction with constant amplitude i.e. without attenuation.As in wave motion the displacement is a function of space as well as time hence displacement relation is expressed as a combined function of position and time asy xt  A sin kx  t  We may also choose a cosine function instead of sine function. Here A K  and  are four constant for a given wave and are known as amplitude angular wave number angular frequency and initial phase angle of given wave."}, {"id": 243, "question": "Relation between phase and path difference", "answer": " A wave motion can be reflected from a rigid as well as from a free boundary. A travelling wave at a rigid boundary or a closed end is reflected with a phase reversal but the reflection at an open boundary takes place without any phase change."}, {"id": 244, "question": "The Principle of Superposition of Wave", "answer": "When any number of waves meet simultaneously at a point in a medium the net displacement at a given time is the algebraic sum of the displacements due to each wave at that time."}, {"id": 245, "question": "Standing waves or Stationary waves", "answer": "When two sets of progressive wave trains of the same type i.e. both longitudinal or both transverse having the same amplitude and time periodfrequency wavelength travelling with same speed along the same straight line in opposite directions superimpose a new set of waves are formed. These are called stationary waves or standing waves."}, {"id": 246, "question": "Progressive Waves", "answer": "1. The disturbance progresses on wards it being handed over from particle to particle. Each particle executes the same type of vibration as the preceding one though at a different time.2. The waves are in the form of crests and troughs i.e. sinecosine functions which move on wards with a definite velocity.3. Every particle has the same amplitude which it attains in its own time depending upon the progress of the wave.4. The phase of every particle varies continuously from 0 to 2 .5. No particle remains permanently at rest. Twice during each vibration the particles are momentarily at rest. Different particles attain this position at different times.6. All the particles have the same maximum velocity which they attain one after another as the wave advances.7. There is a regular flow of energy across every plane along the direction of propagation of the wave. The average energy in a wave is half potential and half kinetic. Waves Characteristics of wave Mechanical waves Electromagnetic Waves Matter waves Transverse wave motion Longitudinal wave motion Wavelength Wave Velocity Amplitude Frequency Time Period Newtons Formula for the velocity of sound in Air11 Factors Influencing Velocity of Sound General Equation of Progressive Waves Relation between phase and path difference The Principle of Superposition of Wave Standing waves or Stationary wavesProgressive Waves"}, {"id": 247, "question": "Stationary Waves", "answer": "1. The disturbance is stationary there being no forward or backward movement of the wave. Each particle has its own vibration characteristics.2. The waves have the appearance of a sinecosine function which shrink to a straight line twice in each vibration. It never advances.3. Every particle has a fixed allotted amplitude. Some have zero amplitude nodes aiJ some have maximum amplitude antinodes always. Each partic1eattains this at the same given moment.4. All the particles in onehalf of the waves have a fixed phase and all the particles in the other half of the wave have the same phase in the opposite direction simultaneously.5. There are particles which are permanently at rest nodes and all other particles have their own allotted maximum displacement which they attain simultaneously. These particles are momentarily at rest twice in each vibration all at the same time.6. All the particles attain their individual allotted velocities depending upon their positions simultaneously. Two particles nodes in one wave form have zero velocities all the time.7. There is no flow of energy at all across any plane. Each particle has its own allotted individual energy. They all attain their values of RE. at one time and all energy becomes KB. at another given time.Stationary Waves When a stationary wave is set up in a string of length l fixed at its two ends in the simplest mode of vibration nodes are formed at the fixed ends and an antinode is formed at the middle point. The frequency of fundamental mode of vibration or first harmonic is given by"}, {"id": 248, "question": "Frequency of the Stretched String", "answer": "In general if the string vibrates in P loops the frequency of the string under that mode is given byBased on this relation three laws of transverse vibrations of stretched strings arise. They are law of length law of tension and law of mass."}, {"id": 249, "question": "Law of Length", "answer": "The fundamental frequency v is inversely proportional tothe length L of the stretched string."}, {"id": 250, "question": "Law of Tension", "answer": "The fundamental frequency is directly proportional to the square root of the tension in the string."}, {"id": 251, "question": "Law of Mass", "answer": "The fundamental frequency is inversely proportional to the square root of mass per unit length of the given string when L and T are kept constants."}, {"id": 252, "question": "Beats", "answer": "The phenomenon of regular rise and fall in the intensity of sound when two waves of nearly equal frequencies travelling along the same line and in the same direction superimpose each other is called beats.One rise and one fall in the intensity of sound constitutes one beat and the number of beats per second is called beat frequency. It is given asvsubbsub vsub1subvsub2subwhere vsub1suband vsub2subare the frequencies of the two interfering waves vsub1subbeing greater than vsub2sub."}, {"id": 253, "question": "Doppler Effect", "answer": "According to Dopplers effect whenever there is a relative motion between a source of sound and listener the apparent frequencies of sound heard by the listener is different from the actual frequency of sound emitted by the source.For sound the observed frequency v is given byHere v  true frequency of wave emitted by the source v  speed of sound through the medium vsub0subthe velocity of observer relative to the medium and vs the velocity of source relative to the medium. In using this formula velocities in the direction OS i.e. from observer towards the source are treated as positive and those opposite to it are taken as negative."}]}